<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-10-12T21:48:42-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Carol Calderon Portfolio</title><subtitle>This is my website, enjoy my projects and thoughts.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Weapons of Math Destruction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Weapons-of-Math-Destruction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Weapons of Math Destruction" /><published>2024-10-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-10-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Weapons-of-Math-Destruction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Weapons-of-Math-Destruction/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-is-a-modelalgorithm-and-how-it-makes-decisions">What is a Model/Algorithm and How It Makes Decisions</h2>

<p>As humans, we continuously learn about the world, and through our interactions, we develop the ability to make decisions—sometimes consciously, sometimes not. Our evolution has now reached a point where we’ve created machines that can also make decisions, using mathematical rules embedded in their systems.</p>

<p>These mathematical systems, also known as algorithms or models, have become more powerful because today’s computers can process larger amounts of data in less time. These models take data as input, apply a set of rules or patterns, and generate outcomes such as scores, decisions, predictions, movements, or even language.</p>

<p>For businesses, the ability to process vast amounts of data quickly and make faster decisions often translates to higher profits and lower operational costs. Consequently, even if we’re unaware, key aspects of our lives are influenced by these algorithms and models—whether in credit scoring, school admissions, job applications, marketing, or even prison sentencing.</p>

<p>🔍 The problem? Many of these models are built on incomplete or biased data, and their inner workings are often opaque. This means the decisions they make, though presented as objective, can actually reinforce inequalities and errors.
Understanding how these models make decisions is the first step toward recognizing their potential for both good and harm.</p>

<h2 id="the-real-world-impact-of-algorithms">The Real-World Impact of Algorithms</h2>

<p>Sometimes, we don’t realize how much these things directly affect us. But this isn’t science fiction—it’s been happening for quite a while. I’m not saying that using algorithms is a problem; they’re a powerful tool for improvement. However, implementing them requires a great deal of accountability and responsibility, as they can unintentionally reinforce and perpetuate discrimination.</p>

<p>In Weapons of Math Destruction, Cathy O’Neil explains how unchecked algorithms disproportionately harm vulnerable populations. The book provides real-life examples of this (and many more):</p>

<p>🎯 Many companies use algorithm-powered personality tests to screen job applicants.</p>

<p>🎯 Credit scores are used to determine not just loan eligibility, but also other life opportunities like renting an apartment or getting a job.</p>

<p>🎯 Sentencing algorithms in some court systems influence the length and severity of prison sentences.</p>

<p>🎯 Hiring algorithms screen job applicants for companies.</p>

<p>💡 Takeaway: It’s important to recognize that these systems, even though they’re based on data, are not neutral. They must be carefully designed, monitored, and regulated to ensure fairness. We’ve known this for a long time, but now, with nearly anyone able to develop and implement these systems, it’s more important than ever to address these issues.</p>

<h2 id="healthcare-algorithms--the-arkansas-case">Healthcare Algorithms – The Arkansas Case</h2>

<p>While the book covers many sectors, one critical area that wasn’t discussed is healthcare, where the impact of algorithms can be life-altering.</p>

<p>In my research, I came across a powerful example: the Arkansas Medicaid algorithm case.</p>

<p>📝 The case: In 2016, Arkansas used an algorithm to determine the number of in-home care hours Medicaid patients would receive. The algorithm’s formula overlooked patient complexities, leading to significant reductions in care for many individuals. This had a devastating impact on their quality of life.</p>

<p>🔎 Lesson: Just like in other areas, healthcare algorithms need transparency and oversight. Without accountability, these systems can cause real-world harm—particularly for vulnerable populations who depend on these decisions.</p>

<p>Want to know more? Check out this detailed report: <a href="https://lnkd.in/eu8iu_Gs">The Guardian: Algorithm crucial in healthcare decisions</a></p>

<p>Source: 📚 These insights are inspired by Cathy O’Neil’s excellent book, Weapons of Math Destruction. If you’re interested in learning more about how these systems affect our lives, I highly recommend checking it out.</p>]]></content><author><name>Carol Calderon</name></author><category term="Big Data" /><category term="Responsible AI" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What is a Model/Algorithm and How It Makes Decisions As humans, we continuously learn about the world, and through our interactions, we develop the ability to make decisions—sometimes consciously, sometimes not. Our evolution has now reached a point where we’ve created machines that can also make decisions, using mathematical rules embedded in their systems. These mathematical systems, also known as algorithms or models, have become more powerful because today’s computers can process larger amounts of data in less time. These models take data as input, apply a set of rules or patterns, and generate outcomes such as scores, decisions, predictions, movements, or even language. For businesses, the ability to process vast amounts of data quickly and make faster decisions often translates to higher profits and lower operational costs. Consequently, even if we’re unaware, key aspects of our lives are influenced by these algorithms and models—whether in credit scoring, school admissions, job applications, marketing, or even prison sentencing. 🔍 The problem? Many of these models are built on incomplete or biased data, and their inner workings are often opaque. This means the decisions they make, though presented as objective, can actually reinforce inequalities and errors. Understanding how these models make decisions is the first step toward recognizing their potential for both good and harm. The Real-World Impact of Algorithms Sometimes, we don’t realize how much these things directly affect us. But this isn’t science fiction—it’s been happening for quite a while. I’m not saying that using algorithms is a problem; they’re a powerful tool for improvement. However, implementing them requires a great deal of accountability and responsibility, as they can unintentionally reinforce and perpetuate discrimination. In Weapons of Math Destruction, Cathy O’Neil explains how unchecked algorithms disproportionately harm vulnerable populations. The book provides real-life examples of this (and many more): 🎯 Many companies use algorithm-powered personality tests to screen job applicants. 🎯 Credit scores are used to determine not just loan eligibility, but also other life opportunities like renting an apartment or getting a job. 🎯 Sentencing algorithms in some court systems influence the length and severity of prison sentences. 🎯 Hiring algorithms screen job applicants for companies. 💡 Takeaway: It’s important to recognize that these systems, even though they’re based on data, are not neutral. They must be carefully designed, monitored, and regulated to ensure fairness. We’ve known this for a long time, but now, with nearly anyone able to develop and implement these systems, it’s more important than ever to address these issues. Healthcare Algorithms – The Arkansas Case While the book covers many sectors, one critical area that wasn’t discussed is healthcare, where the impact of algorithms can be life-altering. In my research, I came across a powerful example: the Arkansas Medicaid algorithm case. 📝 The case: In 2016, Arkansas used an algorithm to determine the number of in-home care hours Medicaid patients would receive. The algorithm’s formula overlooked patient complexities, leading to significant reductions in care for many individuals. This had a devastating impact on their quality of life. 🔎 Lesson: Just like in other areas, healthcare algorithms need transparency and oversight. Without accountability, these systems can cause real-world harm—particularly for vulnerable populations who depend on these decisions. Want to know more? Check out this detailed report: The Guardian: Algorithm crucial in healthcare decisions Source: 📚 These insights are inspired by Cathy O’Neil’s excellent book, Weapons of Math Destruction. If you’re interested in learning more about how these systems affect our lives, I highly recommend checking it out.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/weapons.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/weapons.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Bridging Healthcare and Tech</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/pivoting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bridging Healthcare and Tech" /><published>2024-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/pivoting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/pivoting/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="how-i-pivoted-from-nursing-to-data-science">How I Pivoted from Nursing to Data Science</h2>

<p>Hi there! I’m Carol, let me take you through my story. I began my career as a nurse in Colombia, working 7 years in the clinical field, leading the organ transplant team. It was a role that carried immense responsibility.</p>

<h3 id="the-challenges-that-sparked-my-curiosity">The Challenges That Sparked My Curiosity</h3>

<p>During those years I had the privilege of working with various specialized medical teams, each with unique expertise. I faced and witnessed several challenges in healthcare, challenges I frequently found could be solved by improving our data processes.</p>

<p>So, I wanted to improve several processes, but I realized I didn’t have the skills or knowledge, particularly regarding data and technology. It was frustrating—knowing there were better solutions, but not knowing how to implement them.</p>

<h3 id="the-turning-point-discovering-data-science">The Turning Point: Discovering Data Science</h3>

<p>I saw the opportunities for change, and I was less comfortable in my role. I knew I wanted to be part of the change but I didn’t know where I could start.</p>

<p>Curiosity and my willingness to ask questions helped me to find the path I was looking for. I discovered data science, it opened my eyes to a new world of possibilities. At that time it was not as popular as it is now, then for my peers, I was a bit crazy.</p>

<p>Also during the pandemic, working from home gave me time to reflect. I realized that a better work-life balance was possible, and I could keep working on my passion for improving health care at the same time I could explore new professional paths.</p>

<p>After a lot of reflection, I told my husband about my new goals and dreams. I was committed to learning English and transitioning into data science. We began exploring options and we found them.</p>

<h3 id="starting-from-scratch-in-a-new-country">Starting from Scratch in a New Country</h3>

<p>We saw in Canada alignment with our values and interests. Toronto became our adventure destination. I adapted quickly to the city and started enjoying this place from day one. My favourite things about this city? Cultural diversity, nature and food.</p>

<p>But I had to start from scratch. I dedicated 6 intensive months to learning English and applied my nursing background to working as a caregiver. I also learned about how to learn more efficiently, not everyone has the same learning style and finding mine was beneficial.</p>

<h3 id="taking-the-leap-enrolling-in-data-science">Taking the Leap: Enrolling in Data Science</h3>

<p>As soon as I felt I was ready, I enrolled in a data science diploma. I was hesitant—this was so different from nursing—but I pushed through, and I excelled in applying new skills and working on projects with people from different backgrounds and fields of expertise.</p>

<p>For my final project, I applied machine learning techniques to optimize the emergency department admission process. It was rewarding to see that my background as a nurse gave me insights that enriched the final predictive model.</p>

<h3 id="a-new-role-teaching-assistant-and-data-analyst">A New Role: Teaching Assistant and Data Analyst</h3>

<p>Soon after, as I did great as a student I became a teaching assistant at the data science school. This opportunity made me feel so proud of myself and more confident about my new abilities. I worked there for 3 months.</p>

<p>Then I landed at Surgical Safety Technologies as a Medical Data Analyst. SST is a Canadian company developing AI solutions to improve surgical care. What SST is doing is amazing and their products are saving lives and making surgeries safer.</p>

<h3 id="lessons-from-my-journey">Lessons from My Journey</h3>

<p>I remember the first time I was reading about data science, I had no idea how to organize all of that in my mind. But that’s the process, start at any point and be patient and consistent.</p>

<p>Of course, this process hasn’t been easy. There were times when things felt uncertain. The journey isn’t a straight line, but every step is valuable, bringing you closer to where you want to be.</p>

<h3 id="embrace-curiosity-and-opportunities">Embrace Curiosity and Opportunities</h3>

<p>This story could sound a bit extreme, migrating also means sacrificing a lot, but when unlocking opportunities we do not necessarily need to make huge changes, small changes can be quite fun as well.</p>

<p>Opportunities don’t just appear; we have to be willing to be uncomfortable and go outside our comfort zone. Be curious. Build relationships. Take risks. I would say that the best place to find ideas and opportunities is through others.</p>

<h3 id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h3>

<p>Today, I’m Proud of my transition from nursing to data science. With the AI boom, I feel so happy to be part of this when it’s crucial to ensure diverse representation in tech to make sure innovations are human-centred approach, responsible and ethical.</p>

<p>So, I’ll keep exploring, open to opportunities to advance my technical skills, enjoy my life and positively impact our society using data science. Don’t hesitate to reach out to me if you are interested in this like me.</p>]]></content><author><name>Carol Calderon</name></author><category term="Career development" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How I Pivoted from Nursing to Data Science]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/speaker.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/speaker.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Mind For Numbers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/numbers_mind/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Mind For Numbers" /><published>2023-09-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/numbers_mind</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/numbers_mind/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="breaking-free-from-math-brain-stereotypes">Breaking Free from ‘Math Brain’ Stereotypes</h2>

<p>We usually believe that those who work with numbers are blessed with a special kind of brain. If you don’t possess that “math brain”, it is better to stay away from the topic. Although I excelled in various subjects, math posed a unique challenge then when I chose my career I thought in those subjects where my learning was easier. I consired I had a Biology Brain. However, I remained curious.</p>

<p>As I progressed through university, I explored diverse courses, embracing the idea that I could learn anything. Yet, when faced with complex subjects, I relied on my strengths and avoided deeper mathematical exploration. It wasn’t until I worked as a nurse in the organ transplant unit that I realized the significance of math. I saw that data could drive solutions to many issues, leading me to the world of Data Science.</p>

<p>Embracing this new field came with challenges. My unfamiliarity with the subject and the need for technological literacy left me feeling overwhelmed. I was determined not to shy away this time. I sought to understand the intricacies of this new world, recognizing that I needed fresh learning strategies and tools, recognizing that my limitations weren’t innate but rather a matter of approach. Expanding my options I found a great book.</p>

<p>Barbara Oakley, a professor of engineering at Oakland University, initially disliked math but later discovered her aptitude for it at the age of 26. Her journey, from a degree in Russian linguistics to becoming a widely recognized electrical engineer, resonated with me. Her book, which I encountered during my transition from nursing to data science, provided crucial learning techniques and encouraged me to wholeheartedly pursue my goals. Oakley’s story has been a remarkable source of inspiration and motivation.</p>

<p>While flipping through the book, I took note of some clever strategies she talked about, and I gave them a try. Now, I’d like to share these fantastic ideas with you. I’m not trying to summarize the entire book; I just hope to spark your interest in picking it up for yourself.</p>

<h2 id="key-learning-strategies">Key Learning Strategies</h2>

<h3 id="believe-in-the-capacity-of-your-brain">Believe in the capacity of your brain</h3>

<p>The brain is a marvelous organ. Every day, it performs extraordinary calculations, often without us even realizing it, for example, when you are driving. Recognizing your potential is the first step and the most important. You need to really believe that you can learn anything you want; you just need to understand how the brain learns and take advantage of that to make the most of your time and your effort. Understanding your brain’s functioning maximizes your learning potential while fostering patience and self-compassion.</p>

<h3 id="different-thinking-styles">Different Thinking Styles</h3>

<p>It’s essential not to compare yourself to those individuals who seem to grasp everything instantly. If you find your thinking process to be slower, focusing on details, remember that this can lead to deeper and more creative learning experiences.</p>

<h3 id="molding-your-brain">Molding Your Brain</h3>

<p>Just like your body can be sculpted through nutrition and training, your brain can acquire various skills. Modern neuroscience reveals the incredible plasticity of the brain, showing that it can adapt and learn new abilities.</p>

<h3 id="balancing-rest-and-focus">Balancing Rest and Focus</h3>

<p>Learning effectively involves balancing focused and diffuse thinking. Establish a study schedule that includes dedicated time for breaks. Personally, I’ve discovered that my most insightful moments often occur during everyday activities such as cleaning, walking, or exercising.</p>

<h3 id="building-strong-foundations">Building Strong Foundations</h3>

<p>You need basic concepts before moving further to more complex abstractions. Think of mathematics as an abstract language. You can’t simply jump into the topic and expect to grasp everything without knowing how to navigate through it. It’s crucial to master the fundamental building blocks. Initially, memorization is key, followed by the logical interconnection of these concepts.</p>

<h3 id="memory-and-learning-techniques">Memory and Learning Techniques</h3>

<p>Visualize your brain as a computer: RAM represents your working memory, and the hard disk symbolizes your long-term memory. When you encounter a new concept, it occupies all your working memory. As it becomes familiar and links with existing knowledge in your long-term memory, it swiftly moves there. This involves forming compact knowledge chunks, freeing up working memory space. Initially, learning may feel overwhelming, but once you understand it, you can easily consider additional related variables.</p>

<h3 id="the-process-to-create-chunks-of-knowledge">The Process to Create Chunks of Knowledge</h3>

<ol>
  <li>Focus your attention: work through a key problem on paper, you can know the solution.</li>
  <li>Understand the basic idea: repeat the problem, paying attention to the key processes.</li>
  <li>Take a break / Get a good night’s sleep.</li>
  <li>Practice: repeat the problem again the next day.</li>
  <li>Introducing a new problem.</li>
  <li>Continue with active repetitions.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="boosting-memory">Boosting Memory</h3>

<ol>
  <li>Sleep is fundamental for memory consolidation.</li>
  <li>Spaced repetition and intentional recall are powerful techniques.</li>
  <li>It’s better to have smaller doses of study every day rather than cramming everything into one session.</li>
  <li>Test yourself.</li>
  <li>Utilize visual-spatial memory techniques.</li>
  <li>Create a “palace of memory” by associating information with specific locations.</li>
  <li>Memorize material by creating meaningful connections and associations.</li>
  <li>Use analogies to deepen your understanding.</li>
  <li>Group related information together to create meaningful chunks.</li>
  <li>Engage muscle memory by writing by hand.</li>
  <li>Beware of the illusion of competence. Don’t fool yourself into thinking you understand something when you don’t.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="procrastination">Procrastination</h3>

<p>Procrastination is an enemy we all battle. We often procrastinate to avoid the pain of learning something new, but even in smaller doses, it can be damaging. To combat procrastination, create routines, avoid distractions, reward yourself, use the Pomodoro technique, and don’t focus too much on the results. Instead, enjoy the process of learning, be open to making mistakes, and make sure to include time for diffuse thinking. Multitasking isn’t effective, so set up a dedicated study place, tackle difficult tasks first, plan your weekly tasks, and discover the best strategies that work for you.</p>

<h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>

<p>Transformation is a word that describes many stages and achievements in my life. As I navigate this journey, I’ve already noticed some incredible progress. It’s taken a lot of dedication and perseverance, but the results are truly impressive and rewarding.Transforming my mind has proven to be one of the most challenging goals I’ve ever set for myself. However, today I can confidently say that I have a mind suited for numbers, science, technology, communication, health, the care of life, and any subject I choose to explore.</p>

<p>Lastly, If you are experiencing a similar situation, consider Dra. Oakley’s book as a valuable mentor, and don’t hesitate to connect with me. I’d love to discuss my experiences and share other useful tips.</p>

<h2 id="my-favorite-book-quote">My Favorite Book Quote</h2>

<p><img src="https://carolmargeth.github.io/professionalwebsite/assets/images/Lady_lucks.jpg" alt="Alt text" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p><small>Image Credits:<a href="https://quotefancy.com/quote/2727544/Barbara-Oakley-The-Law-of-Serendipity-Lady-Luck-favors-the-one-who-tries"> Quote Fancy</a></small></p>

<h2 id="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement</h2>

<p>Oakley, Barbara A. “A mind for numbers : how to excel at math and science (even if you flunked algebra).” New York : Jeremy P. Tarcher/Penguin, 2014.</p>]]></content><author><name>Carol Calderon</name></author><category term="Learning" /><category term="Mathematics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Breaking Free from ‘Math Brain’ Stereotypes We usually believe that those who work with numbers are blessed with a special kind of brain. If you don’t possess that “math brain”, it is better to stay away from the topic. Although I excelled in various subjects, math posed a unique challenge then when I chose my career I thought in those subjects where my learning was easier. I consired I had a Biology Brain. However, I remained curious. As I progressed through university, I explored diverse courses, embracing the idea that I could learn anything. Yet, when faced with complex subjects, I relied on my strengths and avoided deeper mathematical exploration. It wasn’t until I worked as a nurse in the organ transplant unit that I realized the significance of math. I saw that data could drive solutions to many issues, leading me to the world of Data Science. Embracing this new field came with challenges. My unfamiliarity with the subject and the need for technological literacy left me feeling overwhelmed. I was determined not to shy away this time. I sought to understand the intricacies of this new world, recognizing that I needed fresh learning strategies and tools, recognizing that my limitations weren’t innate but rather a matter of approach. Expanding my options I found a great book. Barbara Oakley, a professor of engineering at Oakland University, initially disliked math but later discovered her aptitude for it at the age of 26. Her journey, from a degree in Russian linguistics to becoming a widely recognized electrical engineer, resonated with me. Her book, which I encountered during my transition from nursing to data science, provided crucial learning techniques and encouraged me to wholeheartedly pursue my goals. Oakley’s story has been a remarkable source of inspiration and motivation. While flipping through the book, I took note of some clever strategies she talked about, and I gave them a try. Now, I’d like to share these fantastic ideas with you. I’m not trying to summarize the entire book; I just hope to spark your interest in picking it up for yourself. Key Learning Strategies Believe in the capacity of your brain The brain is a marvelous organ. Every day, it performs extraordinary calculations, often without us even realizing it, for example, when you are driving. Recognizing your potential is the first step and the most important. You need to really believe that you can learn anything you want; you just need to understand how the brain learns and take advantage of that to make the most of your time and your effort. Understanding your brain’s functioning maximizes your learning potential while fostering patience and self-compassion. Different Thinking Styles It’s essential not to compare yourself to those individuals who seem to grasp everything instantly. If you find your thinking process to be slower, focusing on details, remember that this can lead to deeper and more creative learning experiences. Molding Your Brain Just like your body can be sculpted through nutrition and training, your brain can acquire various skills. Modern neuroscience reveals the incredible plasticity of the brain, showing that it can adapt and learn new abilities. Balancing Rest and Focus Learning effectively involves balancing focused and diffuse thinking. Establish a study schedule that includes dedicated time for breaks. Personally, I’ve discovered that my most insightful moments often occur during everyday activities such as cleaning, walking, or exercising. Building Strong Foundations You need basic concepts before moving further to more complex abstractions. Think of mathematics as an abstract language. You can’t simply jump into the topic and expect to grasp everything without knowing how to navigate through it. It’s crucial to master the fundamental building blocks. Initially, memorization is key, followed by the logical interconnection of these concepts. Memory and Learning Techniques Visualize your brain as a computer: RAM represents your working memory, and the hard disk symbolizes your long-term memory. When you encounter a new concept, it occupies all your working memory. As it becomes familiar and links with existing knowledge in your long-term memory, it swiftly moves there. This involves forming compact knowledge chunks, freeing up working memory space. Initially, learning may feel overwhelming, but once you understand it, you can easily consider additional related variables. The Process to Create Chunks of Knowledge Focus your attention: work through a key problem on paper, you can know the solution. Understand the basic idea: repeat the problem, paying attention to the key processes. Take a break / Get a good night’s sleep. Practice: repeat the problem again the next day. Introducing a new problem. Continue with active repetitions. Boosting Memory Sleep is fundamental for memory consolidation. Spaced repetition and intentional recall are powerful techniques. It’s better to have smaller doses of study every day rather than cramming everything into one session. Test yourself. Utilize visual-spatial memory techniques. Create a “palace of memory” by associating information with specific locations. Memorize material by creating meaningful connections and associations. Use analogies to deepen your understanding. Group related information together to create meaningful chunks. Engage muscle memory by writing by hand. Beware of the illusion of competence. Don’t fool yourself into thinking you understand something when you don’t. Procrastination Procrastination is an enemy we all battle. We often procrastinate to avoid the pain of learning something new, but even in smaller doses, it can be damaging. To combat procrastination, create routines, avoid distractions, reward yourself, use the Pomodoro technique, and don’t focus too much on the results. Instead, enjoy the process of learning, be open to making mistakes, and make sure to include time for diffuse thinking. Multitasking isn’t effective, so set up a dedicated study place, tackle difficult tasks first, plan your weekly tasks, and discover the best strategies that work for you. Final Thoughts Transformation is a word that describes many stages and achievements in my life. As I navigate this journey, I’ve already noticed some incredible progress. It’s taken a lot of dedication and perseverance, but the results are truly impressive and rewarding.Transforming my mind has proven to be one of the most challenging goals I’ve ever set for myself. However, today I can confidently say that I have a mind suited for numbers, science, technology, communication, health, the care of life, and any subject I choose to explore. Lastly, If you are experiencing a similar situation, consider Dra. Oakley’s book as a valuable mentor, and don’t hesitate to connect with me. I’d love to discuss my experiences and share other useful tips. My Favorite Book Quote Image Credits: Quote Fancy Acknowledgement Oakley, Barbara A. “A mind for numbers : how to excel at math and science (even if you flunked algebra).” New York : Jeremy P. Tarcher/Penguin, 2014.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/brain2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/brain2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>