<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-09-21T14:05:24-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Carol Calderon Portfolio</title><subtitle>This is my website, enjoy my projects and thoughts.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A mind for numbers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/designing-a-flag/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A mind for numbers" /><published>2023-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/designing-a-flag</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/designing-a-flag/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="a-mind-for-numbers">A Mind For Numbers</h1>

<p>We usually believe that those who work with numbers are blessed with a special kind of brain. If you don’t possess that “math brain”, it is better to stay away from the topic. Although I excelled in various subjects, math posed a unique challenge then when I chose my career I think in those subjects where my learning was easier. However, I remained curious.</p>

<p>As I progressed through university, I explored diverse courses, embracing the idea that I could learn anything. Yet, when faced with complex subjects, I relied on my strengths and avoided deeper mathematical exploration. It wasn’t until I worked as a nurse in the organ transplant unit that I realized the significance of math. I saw that data could drive solutions to many issues, leading me to the world of Data Science.</p>

<p>Embracing this new field came with challenges. My unfamiliarity with the subject and the need for technological literacy left me feeling overwhelmed. I was determined not to shy away this time. I sought to understand the intricacies of this new world, recognizing that I needed fresh learning strategies and tools, recognizing that my limitations weren’t innate but rather a matter of approach.</p>

<p>Barbara Oakley, a professor of engineering at Oakland University, initially disliked math but later discovered her aptitude for it at the age of 26. Her journey, from a degree in Russian linguistics to becoming a widely recognized electrical engineer, resonated with me. Her book, which I encountered during my transition from nursing to data science, provided crucial learning techniques and encouraged me to wholeheartedly pursue my goals. Oakley’s story has been a remarkable source of inspiration and motivation.</p>

<p>While flipping through the book, I took note of some clever strategies she talked about, and I gave them a try. Now, I’d like to share these fantastic ideas with you. I’m not trying to summarize the entire book; I just hope to spark your interest in picking it up for yourself.</p>

<h2 id="believe-in-the-capacity-of-your-brain">Believe in the capacity of your brain:</h2>

<p>The brain is a marvelous organ. Every day, it performs extraordinary calculations, often without us even realizing it, for example, when you are driving. Recognizing your potential is the first step and the most important. You need to really believe that you can learn anything you want; you just need to understand how the brain learns and take advantage of that to make the most of your time and your effort. Understanding your brain’s functioning maximizes your learning potential while fostering patience and self-compassion.</p>

<h2 id="different-thinking-styles">Different Thinking Styles:</h2>

<p>It’s essential not to compare yourself to those individuals who seem to grasp everything instantly. If you find your thinking process to be slower, focusing on details, remember that this can lead to deeper and more creative learning experiences.</p>

<h2 id="molding-your-brain">Molding Your Brain:</h2>

<p>Just like your body can be sculpted through nutrition and training, your brain can acquire various skills. Modern neuroscience reveals the incredible plasticity of the brain, showing that it can adapt and learn new abilities.</p>

<h2 id="balancing-rest-and-focus">Balancing Rest and Focus:</h2>

<p>Learning effectively involves balancing focused and diffuse thinking. Establish a study schedule that includes dedicated time for breaks. Personally, I’ve discovered that my most insightful moments often occur during everyday activities such as cleaning, walking, or exercising.</p>

<h2 id="building-strong-foundations">Building Strong Foundations:</h2>

<p>You need basic concepts before moving further to more complex abstractions. Think of mathematics as an abstract language. You can’t simply jump into the topic and expect to grasp everything without knowing how to navigate through it. It’s crucial to master the fundamental building blocks. Initially, memorization is key, followed by the logical interconnection of these concepts.</p>

<h2 id="memory-and-learning-techniques">Memory and Learning Techniques:</h2>

<p>Visualize your brain as a computer: RAM represents your working memory, and the hard disk symbolizes your long-term memory. When you encounter a new concept, it occupies your working memory. As it becomes familiar and links with existing knowledge in your long-term memory, it swiftly moves there. This involves forming compact knowledge chunks, freeing up working memory space. Initially, learning may feel overwhelming, but once you understand it, you can easily consider additional related variables.</p>

<h2 id="the-process-to-create-chunks-of-knowledge">The process to create chunks of knowledge:</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Focus your attention: work through a key problem on paper, you can know the solution.</li>
  <li>Understand the basic idea: repeat the problem, paying attention to the key processes.</li>
  <li>Take a break / Get a good night’s sleep.</li>
  <li>Practice: repeat the problem again the next day.</li>
  <li>Introducing a new problem.</li>
  <li>Continue with active repetitions.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="boosting-memory">Boosting Memory:</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Sleep is fundamental for memory consolidation.</li>
  <li>Spaced repetition and intentional recall are powerful techniques.</li>
  <li>It’s better to have smaller doses of study every day rather than cramming everything into one session.</li>
  <li>Test yourself.</li>
  <li>Utilize visual-spatial memory techniques.</li>
  <li>Create a “palace of memory” by associating information with specific locations.</li>
  <li>Memorize material by creating meaningful connections and associations.</li>
  <li>Use analogies to deepen your understanding.</li>
  <li>Group related information together to create meaningful chunks.</li>
  <li>Engage muscle memory by writing by hand.</li>
  <li>Beware of the illusion of competence. Don’t fool yourself into thinking you understand something when you don’t.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="procrastination">Procrastination:</h2>

<p>Procrastination is an enemy we all battle. We often procrastinate to avoid the pain of learning something new, but even in smaller doses, it can be damaging. To combat procrastination, create routines, avoid distractions, reward yourself, use the Pomodoro technique, and don’t focus too much on the results. Instead, enjoy the process of learning, be open to making mistakes, and make sure to include time for diffuse thinking. Multitasking isn’t effective, so set up a dedicated study place, tackle difficult tasks first, plan your weekly tasks, and discover the best strategies that work for you.</p>

<p>As I navigate this journey, I’ve already noticed some incredible progress. It’s taken a lot of dedication and sticking with it, but the results are truly impressive. Remember to embrace your talents, nurture your mind, and value the guidance of mentors, whether they’re in person or within the pages of books. Just know that with the right approach, unwavering commitment, and belief in yourself, you can unleash your full potential and find immense satisfaction in the process.</p>]]></content><author><name>Carol Calderon</name></author><category term="work" /><category term="projects" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Mind For Numbers We usually believe that those who work with numbers are blessed with a special kind of brain. If you don’t possess that “math brain”, it is better to stay away from the topic. Although I excelled in various subjects, math posed a unique challenge then when I chose my career I think in those subjects where my learning was easier. However, I remained curious. As I progressed through university, I explored diverse courses, embracing the idea that I could learn anything. Yet, when faced with complex subjects, I relied on my strengths and avoided deeper mathematical exploration. It wasn’t until I worked as a nurse in the organ transplant unit that I realized the significance of math. I saw that data could drive solutions to many issues, leading me to the world of Data Science. Embracing this new field came with challenges. My unfamiliarity with the subject and the need for technological literacy left me feeling overwhelmed. I was determined not to shy away this time. I sought to understand the intricacies of this new world, recognizing that I needed fresh learning strategies and tools, recognizing that my limitations weren’t innate but rather a matter of approach. Barbara Oakley, a professor of engineering at Oakland University, initially disliked math but later discovered her aptitude for it at the age of 26. Her journey, from a degree in Russian linguistics to becoming a widely recognized electrical engineer, resonated with me. Her book, which I encountered during my transition from nursing to data science, provided crucial learning techniques and encouraged me to wholeheartedly pursue my goals. Oakley’s story has been a remarkable source of inspiration and motivation. While flipping through the book, I took note of some clever strategies she talked about, and I gave them a try. Now, I’d like to share these fantastic ideas with you. I’m not trying to summarize the entire book; I just hope to spark your interest in picking it up for yourself. Believe in the capacity of your brain: The brain is a marvelous organ. Every day, it performs extraordinary calculations, often without us even realizing it, for example, when you are driving. Recognizing your potential is the first step and the most important. You need to really believe that you can learn anything you want; you just need to understand how the brain learns and take advantage of that to make the most of your time and your effort. Understanding your brain’s functioning maximizes your learning potential while fostering patience and self-compassion. Different Thinking Styles: It’s essential not to compare yourself to those individuals who seem to grasp everything instantly. If you find your thinking process to be slower, focusing on details, remember that this can lead to deeper and more creative learning experiences. Molding Your Brain: Just like your body can be sculpted through nutrition and training, your brain can acquire various skills. Modern neuroscience reveals the incredible plasticity of the brain, showing that it can adapt and learn new abilities. Balancing Rest and Focus: Learning effectively involves balancing focused and diffuse thinking. Establish a study schedule that includes dedicated time for breaks. Personally, I’ve discovered that my most insightful moments often occur during everyday activities such as cleaning, walking, or exercising. Building Strong Foundations: You need basic concepts before moving further to more complex abstractions. Think of mathematics as an abstract language. You can’t simply jump into the topic and expect to grasp everything without knowing how to navigate through it. It’s crucial to master the fundamental building blocks. Initially, memorization is key, followed by the logical interconnection of these concepts. Memory and Learning Techniques: Visualize your brain as a computer: RAM represents your working memory, and the hard disk symbolizes your long-term memory. When you encounter a new concept, it occupies your working memory. As it becomes familiar and links with existing knowledge in your long-term memory, it swiftly moves there. This involves forming compact knowledge chunks, freeing up working memory space. Initially, learning may feel overwhelming, but once you understand it, you can easily consider additional related variables. The process to create chunks of knowledge: Focus your attention: work through a key problem on paper, you can know the solution. Understand the basic idea: repeat the problem, paying attention to the key processes. Take a break / Get a good night’s sleep. Practice: repeat the problem again the next day. Introducing a new problem. Continue with active repetitions. Boosting Memory: Sleep is fundamental for memory consolidation. Spaced repetition and intentional recall are powerful techniques. It’s better to have smaller doses of study every day rather than cramming everything into one session. Test yourself. Utilize visual-spatial memory techniques. Create a “palace of memory” by associating information with specific locations. Memorize material by creating meaningful connections and associations. Use analogies to deepen your understanding. Group related information together to create meaningful chunks. Engage muscle memory by writing by hand. Beware of the illusion of competence. Don’t fool yourself into thinking you understand something when you don’t. Procrastination: Procrastination is an enemy we all battle. We often procrastinate to avoid the pain of learning something new, but even in smaller doses, it can be damaging. To combat procrastination, create routines, avoid distractions, reward yourself, use the Pomodoro technique, and don’t focus too much on the results. Instead, enjoy the process of learning, be open to making mistakes, and make sure to include time for diffuse thinking. Multitasking isn’t effective, so set up a dedicated study place, tackle difficult tasks first, plan your weekly tasks, and discover the best strategies that work for you. As I navigate this journey, I’ve already noticed some incredible progress. It’s taken a lot of dedication and sticking with it, but the results are truly impressive. Remember to embrace your talents, nurture your mind, and value the guidance of mentors, whether they’re in person or within the pages of books. Just know that with the right approach, unwavering commitment, and belief in yourself, you can unleash your full potential and find immense satisfaction in the process.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/brain2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/brain2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>